בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today is thirty-second day of the Omer, ל"ג
בעומר Lag BaOmer minus one. And we are today's דף daf is
עה, Ayin-Hey, 75. We pick up at the bottom of עד עמוד
ב. Ayin-Daled Amud-Bet.
Soon going to be taking a
haircut tonight, tomorrow.
ל"ג Lag we
pick עד עמוד ב Ayin-Daled Amud-Bet two
lines from the five lines from the bottom, three lines before the
line gets wide, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We've continued to talk about
the whole issue here about whom can marry whom, and who can
marry whom I should say.
And you know the just to say I guess one or two
summary statements about the broad sweep of what we've been talking about.
The משנה Mishnah lists all of these different people, the ten different
gradations, but a lot of what the גמרא Gemara has done has
been to sort of minimize those concerns or maybe that's the wrong
word, but anyway, but
but minimize the scope, narrow the scope of those concerns in the
sense that first of all asserting, you know, nobody really knows what
their יחוס yichus is. We all might be descendants of ממזרים mamzerim
for all we know. Once a family is mixed up and its
identity is lost, you leave it that way. Then even when it
got to the whole issue about אסופי asufi and שתוקי, shtuki, about
people that had you didn't know who their father or father and
mother was, and they were ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim. The גמרא Gemara
first of all said that the category of who even counts as
an אסופי asufi is very limited, it's only a child that's been
left to die as opposed to a child that any care has
been shown that would not be in the category of אסופי. asufi.
And then we introduced the very important statement of רבא, Rava, which
is ממזר ודאי אמרה רחמנא ולא ממזר ספק, mamzer vaday amra rachmana
velo mamzer safek, that anybody that is a ממזר ספק mamzer safek
that there's a doubt to, you don't actually from the Torah's perspective
is one is allowed to marry a ישראל Yisrael
or allowed to marry a ממזר. mamzer. So actually it's not a
problem at all from the Torah's perspective.
And what you would have expected the next move of the גמרא
Gemara to have been would have been to say, okay, that's biblically,
but rabbinically we're concerned that this person might be a ממזר. mamzer.
But rather than framing it that way, the way the גמרא Gemara
actually frames it was מעלה עשו ביוחסין. ma'ala asu beyuchsin. This is
just a higher standard that we adopted when it came to marriage
issues. Which meant that like from the sort of weight of the
ממזר mamzer prohibition we're really sort of not concerned, not biblically and
not rabbinically, you know, and it's really just a sort of separate
type of higher standard that we've adopted, which is important because it
raises gets to issues about people that, you know, have questionable ממזר
mamzer status and how much do you investigate and so on. So
in the גמרא, Gemara, right, a lot of those concerns have been
downplayed. So that's in terms of like the general sweep of what
the גמרא Gemara was doing. And then most recently we ended with
a משנה Mishnah that said the משנה Mishnah was to remind us
on the top of עד עמוד א, Ayin-Daled Amud-Alef, כל האסורין לבוא
בקהל מותרין לבוא זה בזה kol ha'asurin lavo bakahal mutarin lavo zeh
bazeh
that anybody that can't marry into the קהל kahal like the case
would be you know the most obvious is the ממזר mamzer and
the נתין nasin and whatever and the ספק ממזר safek mamzer they
can all marry one another. And then there was a confusing line
because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's forbidden. And the גמרא Gemara
most of yesterday's half of yesterday's דף daf was figuring out what
exactly that debate was. In the end the גמרא Gemara interpreted that
משנה Mishnah in a way that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was really
not forbidding, that it was really talking about people like the עמוני
Amoni and the מואבי Moavi and the אדומי Adomi that had converted
that cannot marry into the general כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael but they
were allowed to marry a ממזר. mamzer. And even though רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda forbids a גר ger and a ממזר, mamzer, he would
allow that type of a גר ger because that type of a
גר ger can't marry into general כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, the general
Jewish community. Okay? So that's one principle, that ממזרים mamzerim and ספק
ממזרים safek mamzerim can marry one another according to the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma according to the way we פוסקין pasken a גר ger
can marry a ממזר. mamzer. And the משנה Mishnah was talking about
a case that everybody would agree, which would be a גר ger
of let's say an עמוני Amoni or מואבי Moavi who can't marry
ישראל Yisrael but can marry a ממזר. mamzer. So that's like who
can marry amongst those that cannot marry into general כלל ישראל. Klal
Yisrael. And then we get to this issue which is going to
be our focus is this statement of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, where
אליעזר Eliezer says ודאי בודאי מותר, vaday bevaday mutar, a ודאי ממזר
vaday mamzer can marry like a ודאי ממזר, vaday mamzer, but a
ודאי ממזר vaday mamzer can't marry a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, and
a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry a ספק ממזר safek mamzer
for the obvious reasons that if you treat it as a normal
ספק, safek, so one of these might be a ממזר mamzer and
the other wouldn't. So how can a ספק safek marry a ודאי
ממזר? vaday mamzer? The ספק safek might be a non-ממזר. mamzer. And
how can a ספק ממזר safek mamzer marry ישראל? Yisrael? He might
be a ממזר. mamzer. How can a ספק ממזר safek mamzer marry
a ספק ממזר? safek mamzer? One of them could be a ממזר
mamzer and the other wouldn't be a ממזר. mamzer. So that's a
very reasonable approach, okay, after of course the first question to ask
is so who the heck can this ספק ממזר safek mamzer marry?
So the answer would be a גר. ger. And according to the
position that says a ממזר mamzer can't marry a גר, ger, the
answer would be basically no one it would seem, right, because they
can't even marry a גר אדומי ger Adomi because if this person
isn't a ממזר mamzer then they're ישראל, Yisrael, so that's like really
like... terrible if you think about it, right? And so that then
once again gets to that approach, which is that's if you treat
this person as like a real genuine ספק safek and you have
to apply the normal rules of ספק. safek. But if your general
approach is like the גמרא Gemara says, מעלה עשו ביוחסין, ma'ala asu
b'yuchsin, right
we're not really treating this as a ספק. safek. ספק safek is
okay. It's just this new חומרא chumra of יוחסין. yuchsin. It allows
us to be more more flexible. So the question is going to
be how we're going to rule about this, but this is actually
the issue we're going to focus on. Yes, David, what did you
want to say? All right, so let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
Five lines from the bottom on ע"ד עמוד ב'. ayin daled amud
bet. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabbanan: בן תשע שנים ויום אחד, Ben tesha
shanim v'yom echad, somebody who is nine years old, which means a
nine-year-old man, boy, whose act of sex is considered an act of
sex, גר, ger,
now this person is either a גר ger or an עמוני Amoni
or מואבי Moavi or מצרי Mitzri or
אדומי, Edomi, כותי, Kuti, נתין, Netin, חלל challal or a ממזר. mamzer.
All of those are people that are not allowed to have that
well
we'll take a look. Any of those people שבא על הכהנת ועל
הלויה ובת ישראל,
she-ba al hakohenet v'al halviyah
u-bat Yisrael, פסלוה. pasluha.
If they had sex, actually no I'm sorry, I read that wrong,
it's not גר ger comma, it's גר עמוני ומואבי מצרי ואדומי. ger
Amoni u-Moavi, Mitzri v'Edomi. It's a convert who comes from עמון, Amon,
מואב, Moav, מצרים Mitzrayim or אדום. Edom. So all of those people,
all of those converts cannot marry into ישראל, Yisrael, okay? So this
would be a forbidden act of sex with a
with a Jewish woman, and or כותי, Kuti, נתין, Netin, a כותי
Kuti is a Samaritan who we'll see later but let's assume for
now is also a possible non-Jew, questionable if they really converted. נתין,
Netin, David said cannot marry in, so so far it's a list
of people that cannot marry Jews, okay? And a חלל challal can
marry a Jew but makes a woman he has sex with into
a חללה. challalah. And a ממזר mamzer is a ממזר. mamzer. So
basically everybody here who cannot marry a normal, you know, naturally born
Jew and a חלל, challal, those type of people, שבאו, she-bau, and
these are boys, so whatever, who are nine years old, so the
act of sex is an act of sex, שבאו על הכהנת ועל
הלויה ובת ישראל, she-bau al hakohenet v'al halviyah u-bat Yisrael, that had
sex with a Jewish woman, פסלוה, pasluha, they have invalidated her for
כהונה, kehunah, because basically any act of forbidden sex here basically like
makes her a חללה challalah or forbidden to a כהן kohen or
a חלל, challal, even though it's a permissible act of sex, makes
her into a חללה challalah and makes her forbidden to a כהן.
kohen. Okay. And the כותי ממזר
Kuti mamzer here, it's both ממזר, mamzer, ממזרות mamzerut from עריות arayot
or ממזרות mamzerut from אשת איש? eshet ish?
Correct. Okay. רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Yossi omer: כל שזרעו פסול פוסל,
Kol she-zar'o pasul, posel, וכל שאין זרעו פסול אינו פוסל. v'chol she-ein
zar'o pasul, eino posel.
Not every forbidden act of sex makes her a חללה, challalah, only
an act of sex that would make the child forbidden. But an
act of sex that would not impact the child would not make
her forbidden. Now what does that mean? It doesn't only mean what...
well we'll see in the גמרא Gemara what the case would be.
Okay. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר: Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer: כל
שאתה נושא בתו אתה
נושא אלמנתו. Kol she-ata nosei bito, ata nosei almanato.
Anybody that you could marry the daughter, you could marry the widow,
meaning if this guy, if this was not just an act of
sex but they were married, the only way we could be discussing
if the woman could now marry a כהן kohen would be if
the guy died. Okay. Got that? Right? If he was married, of
course we're talking about a nine-year-old boy, but okay whatever. So what
it's saying is if you could marry the daughter then if a
כהן kohen could marry the daughter, the כהן kohen could marry
the
mother, okay, but it just describes the mother as the widow of
this man because if it was a case of marriage, the only
way she could be available to a כהן kohen would be if
she became a widow. So if you could marry her daughter you
could marry her, וכל שאי אתה נושא את בתו אי אתה נושא
אלמנתו. v'chol she-ee ata nosei et bito, ee ata nosei almanato. If
you can't marry her daughter you cannot marry her... if you cannot
marry his daughter you can't marry his widow, means if you can't
marry her daughter you can't marry her. Okay, so now we're going
to figure out what the difference is. We start with an act
of forbidden sex that makes the woman forbidden to a כהן. kohen.
According to position number two, only if the child becomes a problem.
And according to position number three, only if the daughter becomes a
problem. So the difference between number two and number three is if
any child or all children are problematic or only if the daughter
is problematic.
And position number one?
Number one is anytime the act of sex is forbidden. Ah. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to point out what the
differences are. Let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
מאי איכא בין תנא קמא ובין רבי יוסי? Mai ika bein Tanna
Kamma u-vein Rabbi Yossi?
So what is the difference between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and
רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi? Presumably any of these acts, the children would
turn out like them, right? Let's go through them. If it's the
person is an עמוני מואבי מצרי ואדומי, Amoni, Moavi, Mitzri v'Edomi, or
a כותי Kuti or a נתין, Netin, the children are also become
an עמוני מואבי מצרי אדומי כותי או נתין. Amoni, Moavi, Mitzri, Edomi,
Kuti o Netin. So the same problem with the children. Okay. If
it's a חלל, challal, the child is a חלל. challal. If it's
a ממזר, mamzer, the child is a ממזר. mamzer. So any single
one of these kids, the child is פסול pasul just like the
father. What's the נפקא מינה? nafka mina? נפקא מינה? nafka mina? So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי איכא בין
תנא קמא ובין רבי יוסי? mai ika bein tanna kamma uvein Rabbi
Yosi? אמר רבי יוחנן מצרי שני איכא בינייהו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan Mitzri
sheini ika beinayhu. If the woman had sex with a second generation
מצרי Mitzri convert, in that case the child is a third generation
מצרי Mitzri convert, and the פסוק pasuk says דור שלישי יבא להם
בקהל ה'. dor shelishi yavo lahem bikhal Hashem. The third generation can
marry. So that's a case where the act of sex was forbidden,
but the child is actually okay because the child is a third
generation. So according to the תנא קמא tanna kamma it makes the
woman a חללה chalala because it was a forbidden act of sex,
but according to the second position, רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, the woman
is not a חללה chalala because the child is כשר, kosher, the
child is a מצרי שלישי. Mitzri shelishi. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this, ושניהם לא למדוה אלא מכהן גדול באלמנה. ushneiahem lo
lamduha ela mikohein gadol be'almana. They both learned it out from the
prohibition by a כהן גדול kohein gadol with an אלמנה almana because
what does it say by a כהן גדול kohein gadol with an
אלמנה? almana? It says ולא יחלל זרעו בעמיו, velo yechalel zaro be'amav,
okay, זרעו בעמיו. zaro be'amav. So the idea of לא יחלל lo
yechalel means that when he has sex with the אלמנה, almana, he
makes her into a חללה. chalala. So, right, okay, that's what we
learn out, although it says זרעו, zaro, which is what we're going
to get to, but the גמרא Gemara makes a דרשה, drasha, שני
חילולין. shenei chilullin. יחלל yechalel like it's seen as a double ל,
lamed, like a double חללה, chalala, he makes her a חללה chalala
and he makes his child a חלל.
chalal. Child becomes a חלל chalal because the mother had been transformed
into a חללה. chalala.
Yes, yes, so this פסוק pasuk teaches us that when a כהן
גדול kohein gadol has sex with an אלמנה, almana, from which we're
going to learn
out a general principle of a forbidden act of sex with a
woman makes her a חללה chalala and makes the child a חלל.
chalal. Okay, so now what is the issue here about the case
of a מצרי שני? Mitzri sheini? Let's take a look.
Okay, ושניהם לא למדוה אלא מכהן גדול באלמנה. ushneiahem lo lamduha ela
mikohein gadol be'almana. תנא קמא סבר, tanna kamma savar, כי כהן גדול
באלמנה, ki kohein gadol be'almana, just like that. מה כהן גדול באלמנה
שבביאתו בעבירה ופוסל בה, ma kohein gadol be'almana shebevi'ato ba'aveira uposeil ba,
since that the paradigm there is that it was a forbidden act
of sex, she becomes the חללה, chalala, אף כל שבביאתו בעבירה פוסל.
af kol shebevi'ato ba'aveira poseil. Any time that there was a forbidden
act of sex, she becomes a חללה. chalala. ורבי יוסי סבר, v'Rabbi
Yosi savar, Rabbi Yosi would be of the opinion, no, you have
to be more like that case, כי כהן גדול באלמנה. ki kohein
gadol be'almana. מה כהן גדול באלמנה שזרעו פסול, ma kohein gadol be'almana
shezaro pasul, from that we learn ולא יחלל זרעו, velo yechalel zaro,
that the child also becomes invalid. So when it's a type of
a forbidden act that makes the child forbidden, ופוסל, uposeil, then that
makes her forbidden. אף
כל שזרעו פסול פוסל.
af
kol shezaro pasul poseil.
Any case that the child becomes forbidden, she becomes forbidden. לאפוקי מצרי
שני שאין זרעו פסול, la'apokei Mitzri sheini she'ein zaro pasul, but by
a second generation מצרי Mitzri who had sex with a woman, the
child is not a problem. דאמר קרא בנים אשר יולדו להם דור
שלישי יבא להם בקהל ה', de'amar kra banim asher yivaldu lahem dor
shelishi yavo lahem bikhal Hashem, third generation is permissible. Okay, so what
do you learn from the כהן גדול באלמנה? kohein gadol be'almana? Is
it any forbidden act of sex makes the woman a חללה, chalala,
or only a forbidden act of sex that would impact the child?
Okay, and therefore, in a case here where it's not a case
of a כהן kohein with a woman, it's a normal, whatever, ישראל
Yisrael with a woman, and the forbidden act is not an איסור
כהונה, issur kehuna, then we have to ask the question: Does that
איסור issur pass down, that status pass down to the child? And
since by the case of the מצרי, Mitzri, the status does not
pass down to the child, the woman does not become forbidden. Okay,
so position number one is,
what makes a woman a חללה? chalala? Okay, so the תנא קמא
tanna kamma says, forbidden sex. Okay, one could ask, really? Like even
a case of, like, נדה niddah or something? But all right, but
maybe that would be a little bit different, that's not a sort
of a permanent status or whatever. Okay, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says,
forbidden sex
plus the status passes to the child.
Status passes
to
the
child, that's
זרעו פסול. zaro pasul. This is ביאתו
בעבירה. bi'ato
ba'aveira.
Okay,
and now we're going to look at the third position, which is
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, who says the daughter
has to be forbidden.
Yes, so according to the second, according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
then,
according to the
תנא קמא, tanna kamma, the so-to-speak metaphysical genetics, so-to-speak, will pass on
forever, even past the דור שלישי? dor shelishi?
No, no, he doesn't say the child becomes forbidden, he just says
that the woman becomes a חללה. chalala.
But if that woman has a child, then the child's a חלל,
chalal, right?
And that child will be a חלל, chalal, would be אסור asur
to a כהן, kohein, it wouldn't be a מצרי שלישי. Mitzri shelishi.
So according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi,
that חללות, chalalut, like, ends at the דור שלישי dor shelishi as
it were. Like it doesn't continue, but from one, no, meaning everyone
agrees.
Is that if the mother becomes a חללה, chalalah, the child becomes
a חלל. chalal. The question is here, the normal way we would
assume a woman becomes a חללה chalalah is through a forbidden act
of sex that's forbidden from the כהן kohen perspective, like a כהן
גרושה. kohen grushah. That's a classic case where the—well then she's already
a גרושה, grushah, but whatever. Trying to think of another—well כהן גדול
ואלמנה kohen gadol v'almanah is a case because then it has a
broader implication. Anyway, if let's say or a חלל chalal with a
woman makes her into a חללה chalalah except whatever, there's all these
exceptions. Anyway, when you start with like a specific כהן kohen type
of a thing and she becomes a חללה, chalalah, then the child
becomes a חלל. chalal. But here the איסור issur is not specific
to a כהן. kohen. Here the איסור issur is, you know, מצרי,
Mitzri, אדומי, Adomi, etc., ממזר, mamzer, whatnot, right? Although so in that
type of a case, the question is, the first thing you have
to assert is a general forbidden sex not unique to a כהן
kohen can make the woman a חללה. chalalah. Okay, we learn that
from כהן גדול ואלמנה. kohen gadol v'almanah. Okay. Now, the question then
is, is it like if we can agree the woman becomes a
חללה, chalalah, the child becomes a חלל? chalal? But do we say
all types of forbidden sex? So what this is saying is, it's
not like if the child is a חלל, chalal, she's a—if her
child is a חלל, chalal, she's a חללה chalalah because that begs
the question. We have to first decide if she's a חללה. chalalah.
We're saying if the child is a problem because of some other
status—the fact that we're dealing with, you know, some other perspective, the
fact that we're dealing with a מצרי Mitzri or אדומי Adomi or
a ממזר. mamzer. So meaning okay. A case in which the woman
can—according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, the mother can be a חללה
chalalah and the child will not be.
No.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying if the child isn't a problem,
the mother isn't a problem.
If the child is a מצרי שלישי Mitzri shlishi and not a
problem, the mother is not a חללה. chalalah.
Ah, so that aspect of this particular child's status because of the
דין din of מצרי. Mitzri.
When is she
a חללה?
chalalah? What are the criteria for a woman becoming a חללה? chalalah?
According to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, it's when it was an
act of forbidden sex. Period. According to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it's
when an act of forbidden sex and the status, not the חללות
chalilut status because that begs the question, the other איסור issur status
that we're dealing with, this status what made it forbidden passes to
the child. That's when she becomes a חללה. chalalah. Otherwise, she's not
a חללה. chalalah. So it's not that she's a חללה chalalah and
the child isn't. When the child doesn't have a problem, she's not
a חללה chalalah even
if it was an
act of forbidden sex for the mother. Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says...
Yes. You're confused? Really? Okay, yes.
In other words, I'm confused about the relationship between the mother and
the child. I followed this: if the child's not a problem, say
it's the third generation, not going to be a problem, the mother's
not a חללה. chalalah.
Correct. But I thought it was the act of forbidden sex...
No, according to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, only forbidden sex which
results in the status passing to the child makes her a חללה
chalalah according to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. Okay. These are—that's—these are the
criteria, right? Here you have one criterion, here you have two criteria.
Only then is she a חללה. chalalah. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel אומר, omer, כל שאתה נושא בתו אתה נושא אלמנתו
Kol she-attah nosei bito attah nosei almanato וכל שאי אתה נושא בתו
אי אתה נושא אלמנתו. v'chol she-ei attah nosei bito i attah nosei
almanato. The problem has to only be—it's only if the daughter becomes
forbidden does an act of forbidden sex makes the woman forbidden. מאי
איכא בין Mai ika bein רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose ל רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? What would be a case where
the daughter would not be forbidden but a child—a son would? Because
that presumably is the difference. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר עולא:
Amar Ulla: גר עמוני ומואבי איכא בינייהו. Ger Ammoni v'Moavi ika beinaihu.
If we're dealing with a גר ger who is an עמוני Ammoni
and a מואבי Moavi and a Jewish woman, and the child is
a daughter, so the principle is an עמוני Ammoni woman and a
מואבי Moavi woman are not forbidden. Okay. רבי יוסי סבר Rabbi Yose
savar ככהן גדול באלמנה. ki kohen gadol b'almanah. כהן גדול Kohen gadol
with an אלמנה almanah is the paradigm. מה כהן גדול באלמנה שזרעו
פסול ופוסל אף כל שזרעו פסול ופוסל. Mah kohen gadol b'almanah she-zaro
pasul u-posel af kol she-zaro pasul u-posel. So one argument is, yeah,
here too, the son at least will be an עמוני Ammoni or
a מואבי Moavi and will be a problem, so therefore the mother's
a חללה. chalalah. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says,
no, ככהן גדול באלמנה, ki kohen gadol b'almanah, no, it has to
be like כהן גדול באלמנה. kohen gadol b'almanah. מה כהן גדול באלמנה
שכל זרעו פסול—by Mah kohen gadol b'almanah she-kol zaro pasul כהן גדול
kohen gadol with an אלמנה, almanah, all children, boys and girls, are
problematic, they become חללים. chalalim. אף כל שכל זרעו פסול. Af kol
she-kol zaro pasul. The only time a woman becomes a חללה chalalah
is if all the kids are a problem. Okay. אפילו נקבות, Afilu
nekevot, even the girls. ולאפוקי L'afukei גר עמוני ומואבי, ger Ammoni v'Moavi,
but the case of a גר ger who is an עמוני Ammoni
or מואבי, Moavi, דאיתתא שויא כשירה לבוא בקהל, d'itvta shavei kshira lavo
b'kahal,
that the females can marry, דאמר מר: d'amar mar: עמוני ולא עמונית
מואבי ולא מואבית. Ammoni v'lo Ammonit, Moavi v'lo Moavit.
Only the male Ammonites and Moabites cannot marry but the female can.
So in that case, the mother will be okay. Alright. So רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל—so Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel רבן... Rabban... Gamliel says
you need three things. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you need forbidden
sex and status passes, passes
to
boys
and girls, okay? Because by the כהן גדול באלמנה, Cohen Gadol be'Almanah,
okay, you have you
right? The paradigm of כהן Cohen. of כהן גדול Cohen Gadol באלמנה
is it's forbidden sex. Do you just focus on that or do
you say no, it's not just forbidden sex, it's forbidden sex where
the status passes to a
child? Wait, it's not just the status passes to a child, is
it the case that the status has to pass to both the
boys and the girls? Okay, and each one of these additional criteria
excludes a case. So in this case of a מצרי שני, Mitzri
Sheni, okay, you have forbidden sex,
status does not pass,
does not pass. Okay, so if you only focus on forbidden sex,
חללה. chalalah. If you status on the fact that the status has
to pass, not a חללה chalalah because in this case it doesn't.
Then you have עמוני, Ammoni, okay, in that case, it's forbidden sex,
status goes to the boys, goes passes to the boys, but does
not pass to the girls.
Okay, so in that case, is it forbidden sex? Yes, according to
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma חללה. chalalah. Is it forbidden sex and a
status passes to a child? Yes, so according to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosei it's a חללה. chalalah. Is it forbidden sex and the status
passes to both children? No. So according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel she's not a חללה. chalalah.
Because of the word כל. kol. Yeah, the דרשה's drasha on the
כל. kol.
Well, no, the דרשה's drasha how far do you do you make
the how many similarity points do you need with כהן Cohen גדול
with אלמנה, Almanah, right? How narrowly or broadly do you read that
comparison? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, הכל מודים באלמנת עיסה שפסולה
לכהונה. hakol modim be'Almanas Issa she'psula le'kehuna. Everybody would agree that an
אלמנת עיסה Almanas Issa remember dough means like questionable lineage right? Cannot
marry a כהן. Cohen What does that mean? That means a woman
who had sex with a ספק חלל. sofek chalal. So the the
most sort of obvious case that a woman becomes a חללה chalalah
is she has sex with a חלל. chalal. Then even though the
act is not forbidden, right? Because a חלל chalal can have sex
with a
כהנת Cohenet לוייה Leviyah ישראלית. Yisraelit. There's no איסור, issur, okay? Even
though there's nothing forbidden, the חלל chalal status passes from the man
to the woman.
Okay, so let's say the guy himself is a ספק חלל sofek
chalal and he has sex with a woman. So this woman is
a ספק חללה. sofek chalalah. So she is אסור, assur, okay? So
that's what he says everybody would agree that that case she's אסור.
assur. מאן מיקא בהני תנאי? Man meika be'hani tannai? Who is the
most lenient of these תנאים? Tannaim? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. וקאמר כל שאתה נושא בתו אתה נושא אלמנתו וכל שאין
אתה נושא בתו אין אתה נושא אלמנתו. Ve'ka'amar kol she'atah nosei bito
atah nosei almanato ve'kol she'ein atah nosei bito ein atah nosei almanato.
He says the most lenient, you know,
read is, it's only a problem if the daughter is a problem.
So it seems like he's coming to exclude some case. So what
case is it that he says that actually, you know, would still
be a
problem? למיעוטי מאי? Lemiutei mai? למיעוטי אלמנת עיסה שפסולה לכהונה. Lemiutei Almanas
Issa she'psula le'kehuna. That he would come to say that in the
case of even a case of a ספק, sofek, like she's a
ספק חללה sofek chalalah and the daughter's a ספק חללה, sofek chalalah,
but since you can't marry the daughter, you can't marry the mother.
Okay, so everybody here even though they say some cases aren't a
problem, if the only issue here was ספק, sofek, but it was
a ספק חלל sofek chalal which made the woman a ספק חללה,
sofek chalalah, which made the daughter a ספק חללה, sofek chalalah, in
those types of cases it would be a problem. We'd have to
be מחמיר machmir for the ספק. sofek. לאפוקי מהני תנאי, Le'afukei me'hani
tannai, and that excludes this following position of תנאים. Tannaim. דתנן, De'tnan,
העיד רבי יהושע ורבי יהודה בן בתירה על אלמנת עיסה שכשירה לכהונה.
hei'id Rabbi Yehoshua ve'Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira al Almanas Issa she'kesheira le'kehuna.
A woman, right, she's called a widow because it means she was
married to a כהן Cohen. that was a ספק חלל sofek chalal
and now the כהן Kohen, died, could be divorced her obviously she'd
be a גרושה. grusha. So now she's a ספק חללה, sofek chalalah,
she can marry a כהן. Kohen? Why? So the גמרא Gemara says
why isn't she just a ספק חללה sofek chalalah end of story
and her daughter's a ספק חללה? sofek chalalah? The גמרא Gemara says
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? הוי ספק ספיקא וספק ספיקא לקולא. Havai sefek
sefeka ve'sefek sefeka le'kula. It's a double ספק. sofek. Now it's really
not a double ספק, sofek, it's a derivative of a ספק, sofek,
right? There's only one ספק. sofek. If her husband was a חלל,
chalal, she's a חללה chalalah and her child's a חללה. chalalah. So
the actual real doubt here there's only one question, was her husband
a חלל? chalal? But רש״י Rashi says since it is a derivative
of a ספק, sofek, first you have to say he's a חלל,
chalal, then as a result of him being a חלל chalal she's
going to be a חללה. chalalah. So that's like a status transferred
בספק. bi'sofek. You sort of see that? It's not really a ספק
ספיקא. sefek sefeka. It's a derivative
ספק. sofek. First the ספק sofek was about his status. That's the
first ספק. sofek. The second thing is the the second thing is
we take his doubtful status and one degree removed we apply it.
I would say it's a diluted, it's a diluted status.
Or a derivative, right. It's a derivative I would say. Anyway, according
to this opinion, that is enough to make her permissible. All right,
moving on. So that was a little bit of a digression with
יוחסין כהונה. yuchsin kehunah. Yeah. So that was a little bit of
a digression, I don't know, a digression, it's all about יוחסין, yuchsin,
but that was a specific focus on כהנים kohanim issues and what
makes a חללה chalalah a little bit more from the more sort
of broader focus that we've been having until now. Okay, back to
now the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that really creates a
real challenge for somebody who is a ספק ממזר safek mamzer because
he says we don't treat a ספק ממזר safek mamzer opposed to
the approach earlier in the גמרא, Gemara, which is we basically treat
them as totally okay but we say מעלה עשו ביוחסין. ma'aleh asu
beyuchsin. He treats them as real ספק. safek. And because he treats
them as real ספק, safek, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, he says that
a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry a ודאי ממזר, vaday mamzer,
can't marry a ודאי ישראל, vaday Yisrael, can't even marry a ודאי
ממזר, vaday mamzer, a ספק ממזר safek mamzer because you don't know,
one person yes and one person no. Okay, so according to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer things are really very challenging. So אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב הלכה כרבי אליעזר. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi
Eliezer. Now he says we rule like that. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, so anybody who is a ספק ממזר safek mamzer has
got a real problem,
okay. כי אמריתה קמי דשמואל Ki amritah kamei d'Shmuel and when I
said it to שמואל, Shmuel, אמר לי, amar li, he says, הלל
שנה עשרה יוחסין עלו מבבל וכולם מותרים לבוא זה בזה. Hillel shanah
asarah yuchsin alu miBavel vechulam mutarin lavo zeh bazeh. הלל Hillel says
that ten יוחסין yuchsin came from בבל Bavel and they can all
intermarry. Now רש"י Rashi says, and does his worry, they can't all
intermarry, like a ממזר mamzer can't marry ישראל. Yisrael. So רש"י Rashi
says it means like all the פסולים psulim can intermarry, okay. So
therefore, he says, you know, all the פסולים psulim can intermarry, ואתה
אמרת הלכה כרבי אליעזר? ve'atah amarta halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer? And you're saying
we're going to rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says now
all of a sudden a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry a
ודאי ממזר? vaday mamzer? All right, so the גמרא Gemara says, so
that's a nice debate, how are we going to let's see how
it gets resolved.
ורמי דרב אדרב ורמי דשמואל אדשמואל, Verami deRav aDeRav verami deShmuel aDeShmuel,
a contradiction of רב Rav on his own statement and שמואל Shmuel
on his own statement. דאתמר, De'itmar,
ארוסה שעיברה, Arusah she'ibrah, a woman who was betrothed, halachically she's totally
married, but she and her husband at least as far as we
know have not been sleeping together, they have yet to make, you
know, she's still living in her father's home, they have yet to
actually set up house together, and all of a sudden she becomes
pregnant. A miracle, right, virgin birth. So we'd like to know how
she became pregnant. Was it through her betrothed and the child is
actually כשר, kosher, or was it with another man and the child's
a ממזר? mamzer? So רב אמר הולד ממזר, Rav amar havlad mamzer,
the child's a ממזר mamzer and we assume it's another man. ושמואל
אמר הולד שתוקי. uShmuel amar havlad shtuki. No, he's a ספק ממזר.
safek mamzer. Okay, so now what difference does it make? Either way
he's a ממזר, mamzer, either way he can't marry ישראל. Yisrael. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, presumably here's what they mean.
רב אמר הולד ממזר ומותר בממזרת Rav amar havlad mamzer umutar bemamzeret
that רב Rav is actually being more lenient than שמואל. Shmuel. רב
Rav is saying she's a ממזר mamzer and can marry a ממזרת
mamzeret because we treat her as a ודאי ממזר, vaday mamzer, the
child is a
ודאי ממזר. vaday mamzer. Okay, ושמואל אמר הולד שתוקי ואסור בממזרת. uShmuel
amar havlad shtuki ve'assur bemamzeret. It's a ספק ממזר safek mamzer and
a ספק ממזר safek mamzer would be the worst because might be
a ממזר mamzer might not and therefore can't marry a ממזר. mamzer.
So if that's how you read their debate, then שמואל Shmuel actually
is saying that a ספק ממזר safek mamzer cannot marry a
ודאי ממזר. vaday mamzer. And that was what שמואל Shmuel said the
opposite position a minute ago, that ספק ממזר safek mamzer is not
a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, how are you going to
reconcile that? So the גמרא Gemara says איפוך, ipoch, reverse it. That's
all you have to do. רב אמר הולד שתוקי, Rav amar havlad
shtuki, ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, which is a way of saying because
there's a doubt, cannot marry a ודאי ממזר. vaday mamzer. ושמואל אמר
הולד ממזר, uShmuel amar havlad mamzer, which is not really saying that
he's definitely a ממזר mamzer because that's crazy, we don't know he's
definitely a ממזר, mamzer, maybe it's from her husband, okay. It's really
a way of saying even though it's a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer,
it's okay, he can still marry a ממזר. mamzer. So now they're
consistent. רב Rav says a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't and שמואל
Shmuel says a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can marry a ממזר. mamzer.
Yeah.
I have a little tiny thing. This has always bothered me because
we see this hundreds of times like just איפוך.
ipoch. Yep. Maybe
this
is obvious, but this whole thing was oral. Like I'm reading it
says אמר, amar, right. It's just like he said, no he said,
it's all that it's much more
possible to reverse it, right, right, correct.
It's not a written text.
Absolutely. Of course. Absolutely. Absolutely. So now the גמרא Gemara says תרתי
למה לי tarti lamah li if they really do have reversed positions,
why do they have to repeat it? Meaning why do they have
to say on our משנה Mishna what that you know רב Rav
says ספק ממזר safek mamzer is a problem with ממזרת mamzeret and
שמואל Shmuel says not, and then say it again by this case
of the betrothed, you know, woman. So the גמרא Gemara צריכי, tzerichi,
you need to say it twice. דאי אתמר בהא בהא קאמר רב
משום דרובא כשרים אצלה. De'i itmar beha beha ka'amar Rav mishum de'ruba
ksherim etzlah. Had רב Rav just said that a normal case of
a ספק ממזר safek mamzer is a problem, that's by like a
single woman, that the most likely scenario with a single woman is
that the child isn't a ממזר, mamzer, right? Because a single woman,
how would the child be a ממזר? mamzer? Only if she was
having sex with a relative or with a ממזר. mamzer. So it's
highly unlikely the child is a ממזר. mamzer. So there רב Rav
is going to say in that case, the child can't marry another
ממזר. mamzer. It's a good chance the child's totally okay. אבל התם.
Aval hatam. אבל התם Aval hatam by the case of a betrothed
woman, רוב פסולין אצלה, rov psulin etzla, 99.99% of the world would,
a men would make the child a ממזר. mamzer. The only man
she could have had sex with that the child wouldn't be a
ממזר mamzer in that case is her husband. Okay? So the vast
majority of the population would have made her child a ממזר. mamzer.
So in that case, most likely the child is a ממזר. mamzer.
So therefore, we should let the child marry another ממזר. mamzer. Okay?
אימא מודה ליה לשמואל, Eima modei leh l'Shmuel, maybe he'd agree to
שמואל Shmuel that the child can marry a ממזר mamzer in that
case? So then צריכא, tzricha, you have to know even in that
case, it's enough of a ספק safek that he might be okay
that the child can't marry a ממזר. mamzer. ואי אשמעינן בהא, V'ei
ashmienan b'ha, if you just told me that case about the case
of the betrothed woman, בהא קאמר רב, b'ha ka'amar Rav, that's where
רב Rav says that the child can't marry a ממזר. mamzer. Why?
Because you have the opposite argument. It's more likely in that case
the child's okay משום דאיכא למיתלי בארוס, mishum d'eika lemitli b'arus, because
she's already engaged or betrothed to this other man. So it's reasonable
to think that it's her husband's child. Right? And therefore because it's
reasonable that the child might not be a ממזר, mamzer, he's אסור
assur to marry a ממזר. mamzer. The child can't marry a ממזר.
mamzer. אבל בהא, Aval b'ha, by a random single woman that just
got pregnant, אימא מודה ליה לשמואל, eima modei leh l'Shmuel, there's no
particular man that we can say is the person. So in that
case,
maybe he would agree to שמואל Shmuel that we should assume more
likely it's a ודאי ממזר? vadai mamzer? There's not a particular man
we can sort of pin it on. So maybe therefore it's מותר
בממזר. mutar b'mamzer. צריכא, Tzricha, you have to tell me both cases.
Okay. So now what we're basically saying is sort of like, it
sounds like it's less of a principle debate of what's the status
of a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, but like how much are we
really חושד choshed that the child might be כשר? kasher? שמואל Shmuel
is not so חושד choshed the child might be כשר, kasher, so
it's מותר בממזרת. mutar b'mamzeret. And רב Rav says no, he still
have to worry in this case and this case maybe the child
is כשר kasher and therefore אסור בממזרת. assur b'mamzeret. Okay, that sort
of seems to be the way the גמרא Gemara is framing the
debate. Okay, that's one explanation. ואיבעית אימא לעולם לא תיפוך. V'iba'it eima
l'olam lo teipoch. Don't reverse their positions by the case of the
betrothed woman. ומאי ממזר דקאמר רב? U'mai mamzer d'ka'amar Rav? Now what,
now if that's true, they're not reversing their positions. So you have
this woman who's betrothed, who's pregnant. Okay? רב Rav would say
the child's a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. So רב Rav would say
the child can't marry a ממזרת mamzeret and שמואל Shmuel would say
the child could marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. So fine. So what, so
what are they debating when רב Rav says ממזר mamzer and שמואל
Shmuel says שתוקי? shtuki? So let's take a look. Okay. ומאי ממזר
דקאמר רב, U'mai mamzer d'ka'amar Rav, so when רב Rav there says
ממזר, mamzer, he says לאו מותר בממזרת. lav mutar b'mamzeret. Not to
say that the child can marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. Because that's not
true. A ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. So
why does רב Rav say that this betrothed woman's child is a
ממזר? mamzer? Why does he use that phrase? What's that meant to
convey? Right? אלא דאסור בבת ישראל. Ella d'assur b'bat Yisrael. By saying
ממזר, mamzer, he's saying cannot marry a Jewish woman. It means ספק
ממזר, safek mamzer, don't marry a ישראל. Yisrael. Okay. Then what's שמואל
Shmuel saying? ושמואל אמר הולד שתוקי דאסור בבת ישראל. U'Shmuel amar havlad
shtuki d'assur b'bat Yisrael. So okay, but שמואל's Shmuel saying the same
thing. שתוקי Shtuki is a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, can't marry ישראל.
Yisrael. So now they're not debating. Okay. אי הכי היינו דרב. Ei
hachi hainu d'Rav. Okay, אלא מאי שתוקי? ella mai shtuki? So let's
treat it as something else שמואל Shmuel must mean. Nobody's talking about
marrying a ממזרת. mamzeret. That's not the discussion. They're talking about this
fetus, this child, for a normal ישראל. Yisrael. רב Rav says ממזר,
mamzer, don't marry a normal ישראל. Yisrael. So what's שמואל Shmuel saying?
ושמואל אמר הולד שתוקי, U'Shmuel amar havlad shtuki, I'm sorry, אלא מאי
שתוקי? ella mai shtuki? שמשתקין אותו מדין כהונה. She'meshatkin oto mi'din kehuna.
It means that if the betrothed man or the whatever, the man
she's betrothed to is a כהן, kohen, the child has no right
to the status of כהונה. kehuna. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא,
pshita, of course not. השתא מדין ישראל משתקינן ליה. Hashta mi'din Yisrael
meshatkinan leh. If we don't let him marry a ישראל Yisrael because
he's a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, מדין כהונה מיבעיא? mi'din kehuna mibaya?
Is there only a question that he wouldn't have a status of
a כהן? kohen So how, again, what is שמואל Shmuel adding beyond
what רב Rav already said, if רב Rav already said the child's
a ספק ממזר? safek mamzer? אלא מאי שתוקי? Ella mai shtuki? Here's
what שמואל's Shmuel adding. שמשתקין אותו מנכסי אביו. She'meshatkin oto mi'nichsei aviv.
A similar type of a point, that the betrothed woman's husband, if
he were to die, this child, who not only is he a
ספק ממזר safek mamzer in terms of personal status of who he
can marry, but he's also a ספק ממזר safek mamzer in terms
of being a questionable heir of the father. So if the father
were to die, he would not be entitled to any portion in
the estate. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obviously those go
hand in hand. מי ידעינן אבוה מנו? Mi yadainan avuh manu? Who,
we don't know who his father is. If you're saying he's a
ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, then we don't know that this woman's, the
man the woman's betrothed to is his father. We're doubting that. So
of course he's not going to get a portion in the estate.
Again, what would שמואל Shmuel be adding beyond what רב Rav said?
So the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא דתפס. lo tzricha d'tafas. The
case would be that he let's say seized some of this property.
The father, the assumed father, died. He seized some of the property.
So maybe we should say, Okay, it's a ספק, safek, it might
reasonably be that he, that that's a reasonable that that's the father.
Maybe we're not going to take the property out of this person's
possession. Says no, once it's such a doubt of who the father
is, he has absolutely no right to the estate even if he
seized it. Okay, so according to this read, both רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel would agree that the child
that this betrothed woman is carrying is a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer,
can't marry ישראל, Yisrael, and all that שמואל Shmuel is adding is
he has no rights to the father's estate even if he were
to seize it. But they're not discussing whether he can marry a
ממזרת mamzeret or not, that's not the issue.
ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, and if you want a third explanation, אימא
מאי שתוקי, eima mai shtuki, בדוקי. beduki. No, no, no. By שמואל
Shmuel saying שתוקי, shtuki, now at least שמואל's Shmuel a little bit
more consistent with his point before that he's being lenient. שמואל Shmuel
is actually saying don't just write this guy off as a ממזר,
mamzer, this kid who the betrothed woman is pregnant with. No, ממזר,
mamzer, can't marry anybody end of story. שמואל's Shmuel saying I'm not
ready to write him off yet. שתוקי Shtuki means it's like a
questionable status. What does a questionable status mean? Why are you raising
that point? To say let's investigate, בדוקי. beduki. שבודקין את אמו, she'bodkin
et imo, you check the mother, ואומרת לכשר נבעלתי, v'omeret l'kasher nivalti,
and if the mother says, yeah, the sex I had was permissible,
meaning it was with the man I was betrothed to, then נאמנת,
ne'emenet, she'd be believed. So the גמרא Gemara says: כמאן? כרבן גמליאל?
K'man? K'Rabban Gamliel? You mean he's פסקן-ing paskin like רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel in terms of that debate in כתובות Ketubot of do you
believe the woman? הא אמר שמואל חדא זימנא, Ha amar Shmuel chada
zimna, שמואל Shmuel already said it once, דתנן, d'tenan, היתה מעוברת, hayita
me'uberet, a woman was pregnant, a single woman, ואמרו לה, v'amru lah,
מה טיבו של עובר זה? mah tivo shel ubar zeh? What's the
status of this fetus? And she said, מאיש פלוני וכהן הוא, me'ish
ploni v'kohen hu, it's from such a man, he's a כהן, Kohen,
meaning not specifically that he's a כהן Kohen, but the point is
he's a totally kosher guy, the child is kosher, I'm kosher, etc.
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, so then do we believe her? רבן גמליאל
ורבי אליעזר אומרים נאמנת, Rabban Gamliel v'Rabbi Eliezer omrim ne'emenet, she's believed.
רבי יהושע אומר אינה נאמנת, Rabbi Yehoshua omer einah ne'emenet, she's not
believed. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הלכה
כרבן גמליאל, halacha k'Rabban Gamliel, we rule like רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
Okay, so therefore when שמואל Shmuel is saying so this case of
the woman who's betrothed who's pregnant, רב Rav says ממזר, mamzer, end
of story. Okay, שמואל Shmuel says no, no, no, let's ask her,
and then we'll go by what she says, okay, and that's the
debate.
They got the case in where there was a לשון lashon of
לא על פיה, lo al pi'ha, yeah, exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara says: צריכא, tzaricha, you need to tell me
both cases. דאי מהתם, De'ei mehatam, had it been the case over
there in כתובות Ketubot with the case of the single woman, הוה
אמינא התם רוב כשרים אצלה, hava amina hatam rov k'sherim etzlah, most
people are kosher, right? It's hard for a single woman to have
sex that would actually make the child a problem. אבל הכא דרוב
פסולים אצלה, Aval hacha d'rov p'sulim etzlah, here everybody other than the
man that she's betrothed to would make the child a ממזר. mamzer.
אימא לא, Eima lo, maybe you don't believe her? צריכא, tzaricha, you
need to tell me both cases. Okay, so basically you have a
debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel about a ספק ממזר, safek
mamzer, if a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can marry another ממזר. mamzer.
Okay, that's the debate of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, can he
even marry another ספק ממזר? safek mamzer? How do we פסקן? paskin?
Do we פסקן paskin רב אלעזר Rav Elazar or not? This other
issue about the woman who betrothed woman who's pregnant, the גמרא Gemara
said is a different debate. They're not talking about whether he can
marry a ממזר. mamzer. They're talking about a different question: Can you
ask the mother and go by what the mother says? Okay. Now,
before we move on, the question is how do we פסקן? paskin?
Too bad Michael isn't here. But if we take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says: וכולן מותרין זה בזה, v'kulan mutarin zeh
ba'zeh, if you go four lines down in
תוספות. Tosafot. He says: ונראה דהלכה כרבי אלעזר, V'nira d'halacha k'Rabbi Elazar,
about six lines down in תוספות. Tosafot. ונראה דהלכה כרבי אלעזר, V'nira
d'halacha k'Rabbi Elazar, we rule like רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. דהא רב
פוסק כוותיה, D'ha Rav posek kavatei, והלכה כרב באיסורי לגבי שמואל. v'halacha
k'Rav b'issurei legabi Shmuel. And רמב"ם Rambam rules the same way, and
שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules the same way, that we rule like
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, which is a very harsh ruling, which is
a ספק ממזר safek mamzer cannot marry a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer,
and cannot marry a ודאי ממזר, vadai mamzer, and cannot marry a
ודאי ישראל, vadai Yisrael, right? Because a ספק ממזר safek mamzer might
be a ממזר mamzer so can't marry ישראל, Yisrael, might be a
not a ממזר mamzer and can't marry a ממזר, mamzer, and one
ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry another ספק ממזר safek mamzer because
one might be one and one might be the other. And תוספות
Tosafot and רמב"ם Rambam and שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch all say we
rule that way. Okay? Which basically means the only person a ספק
ממזר safek mamzer can marry is a גר. ger. Right? Is that
going to be a ממזר mamzer from that?
Is that going to be a ממזר mamzer then a ספק ממזר?
safek mamzer? Okay. And how does that fit in with the earlier
גמרא? Gemara? The problem is that a lot of that gets minimized
because we rule that if we rule that you can trust the
mother, so any case we know who the mother is you can
trust the mother. So that minimizes the scope there. And the case
where it's an abandoned child, an אסופי, asufi, we basically say that
anytime that the child looks like it's cared for and wasn't left
to die isn't an אסופי. asufi. So on the one hand, the
ruling of somebody who actually is a שתוקי shtuki or an אסופי
asufi is very harsh. The only person they're left to marry is
a גר. ger. On the other hand, we did a lot to
minimize the scope of those cases. okay, and we said that the
mother could be believed if you פוסקן pasken that way, and that
the child isn't an אסופי asufi if it wasn't left to die,
okay, but again, it's still, it's like this is a very harsh
ruling for somebody who falls into that category. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues as the following. Let's take a look. Yes.
Can I ask a naive question? Yeah, sure. So again, contemporary legal
systems, laws change. What would be the mechanism beyond or other than
narrowing the scope so it's almost not applicable? Like what would be
the mechanism to changing that הלכה? halakha?
I don't know,
I mean that's always the question, you know, you narrow the scope,
you reinterpret the terms, you, you know, if certain cases where you
say context is different or whatever. I mean, you know, that's a
general approach. Right. Or
you פוסקן pasken the other way, although here everybody has פוסקן pasken
this way. All right. All right. So anyway, so all right, so
let's continue. So גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. Right. So
גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, new הלכה. halakha. This is going
to be confusing as if this wasn't until now. I was actually,
actually it was pretty clear until this point. Okay. So גמרא Gemara
says like
this.
Okay. תניא, Tanya, second wide line of the widest line. וכן רבי
אליעזר וכן רבי אלעזר אומר כותי לא ישא כותית. v'chein Rabbi Eliezer
v'chein Rabbi Elazar omer Kuti lo yisa Kutit. A Samaritan cannot marry
another Samaritan. Now again, who the heck is a Samaritan supposed to
marry, right? Maybe could be nobody. I mean, good thing they're not
asking us the הלכה. halakha. I mean, can they marry a גר?
ger? I don't know. What exactly is the status of a Samaritan?
Why can a Samaritan not marry a Samaritan? Okay, we'll have to
figure this out and then we'll have to figure out if there's
anybody left for them to marry. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the
reason? אמר רב יוסף עשאוה כגר לאחר עשרה דורות. amar Rav Yosef
asauha k'ger l'achar asara dorot. They
made it like a גר ger after ten generations. דתניא גר עד
עשרה דורות מותר בממזרת מכאן ואילך אסור בממזרת. d'tanya ger ad asara
dorot mutar b'mamzeret mikan v'eilach asur b'mamzeret. Until ten generations can marry
a ממזרת, mamzeret, afterwards not. ויש אומרים עד שישתקע שם עבודת כוכבים
ממנו. v'yesh omrim ad sheyishtaka shem avodat kochavim mimenu. It's not a
formal definition of ten generations, it's as long as he is still
his the non-Jewish name is forgotten from him, which basically רמב"ם Rambam
says means until the point that it's forgotten that he's a descendant
of גירות. geirus. Now there's a lot of very important הלכות halachot
that have just been said here. Number one, which nobody has asked
until now, is the following question. When we say a ממזר mamzer
can marry a גר, ger, right, does that just mean a first
generation גר? ger? Somebody who has just converted? Or does that mean
anybody who is a descendant of גרים? gerim? So the גמרא Gemara
just has now said that anybody that is descendant of גרים gerim
is also considered to be a גר ger and can marry a
convert. You with me here? Okay, that's a big הלכה. halakha. You
sort of understand it if you say it's an issue of קהל
גרים, kehal gerim, but now the interesting question to ask, which I'm
not going to answer right now, is how do you define if
somebody is a descendant of גר? ger? Does it go by the
father or the mother or both or either? Right? You with me
here everybody, right? If it's not just about the גר ger but
any descendant of a גר ger can marry a ממזר, mamzer, is
it descendants on which side? Both sides, either side, just one side,
which side, etc.? That's one question. Okay. But that's point number one,
is that a descendant of a גר ger can marry a ממזר.
mamzer. Now how do we applying this to a כותי? Kuti? Oh,
but number two is once it is forgotten that this person is
of גר ger descent, he can't, he cannot marry a ממזר. mamzer.
Why not? Why do you think he's he cannot marry a ממזר
mamzer once it's forgotten that he's of גר ger descent?
He might be a ישראל. Yisrael.
Not only he might be, but he might be confused as a
ישראל Yisrael to everybody. Nobody remembers the fact that ten generations ago,
you know, his
grand his great-great-great-great-great-grandfather converted, so they'll just see a ישראל Yisrael married
a ממזר, mamzer, so you can't have that. Once that identity is
lost, we have to treat him as a straight ישראל לחומרא. Yisrael
lachumra. Okay, that's number one. Now how is this relevant to the
כותי Kuti and the כותית Kutit case? So תוספות Tosafot says the
following. He says because
if we assume that כותים Kutim are ספק ממזרים, safek mamzerim, okay,
right, because of... one minute...
one minute,
one
minute... right. Hold on, hold on... Ah,
so the point is like this. He says here's the issue by
the כותים, Kutim, okay? We're not exactly sure. We're going to see
in a minute because of the fact that they might be, you
know, they might not be careful in certain הלכות halachot about marriage
and divorce or whatever, so let's say we treat that כותים Kutim
are also ספק ממזרים, safek mamzerim, right? That would be the easiest
way to say why כותים Kutim can't marry זה בזה. zeh bazeh.
This is the same רב אלעזר Rav Elazar that says a ספק
ממזר safek mamzer can't marry a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, right? Because
one might be a ממזר, mamzer, one might be not. So let's
say you assume that all the כותים Kutim are not careful with
all the הלכות halachot of גיטין וקידושין, gittin v'kiddushin, so there's a
lot of ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim. running around amongst the כותים. Kutim.
So you would say a כותי Kuti can't marry another כותי Kuti
because it's a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. One might be a ממזר,
mamzer, one might not and they can't marry זה בזה. zeh b'zeh.
That's a very reasonable explanation, right? But then the גמרא Gemara says,
but one minute, why is it a problem? All of the כותים
Kutim are גרים, gerim, right? If they've all the כותים Kutim converted,
so even if there's a lot of ספק ממזרים safek mamzerim around
the כותים, Kutim, anybody is either a ממזר mamzer marrying a גר,
ger, I mean a גר ממזר ger mamzer marrying a גר, ger,
or גר ger non-ממזר mamzer marrying a גר, ger, but they're all
marrying גרים gerim because they're all גרים gerim if they marry one
another, all descendants of גרים. gerim. So even if you consider the
כותים Kutim to be ספק ממזרים, safek mamzerim, there's no reason they
can't marry one another, right? Because you're marrying a גר. ger.
Like that גמרא Gemara talking about רב יוסף Rav Yosef and רבן
שמעון
בן גמליאל?
Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel?
Let's not go there.
No, no, no, but then what's there's another
factor.
Right, so basically, so the question is, we know רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry ספק ממזר, safek mamzer,
but why can a כותי Kuti not marry a כותי Kuti even
if you treat them all as ספק ממזרים, safek mamzerim, they're all
גרים. gerim. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is yes, but they're but
it's like a גר אחר עשרה דורות. ger achar asara doros. Their
גירות gerus happened so many generations ago, from the one hand, their
identity hasn't been lost, right? It's not like people they still have
this label of כותי. Kuti. On the other hand, it was so
many generations ago, we're not going to apply the קולא kula of
גרים, gerim, and that's why it's a problem. Okay, so that's רבא's
Ravah answer. Okay, so let's take a look. Was it רבא? Ravah?
Who was it? It says,
the גמרא Gemara says like this:
so yeah, that was that was רב יוסף's Rav Yosef answer. It's
true they're ספק ממזרים, safek mamzerim, but it's after and it's but
it's true that they're גרים, gerim, but it's after so many generations
we don't have the קולא kula of גרים, gerim, and that's why
they can't marry זה בזה. zeh b'zeh. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so אביי Abaye responded back, מי
דמי, mi dami, how can you compare it?
התם, Hasam, גר ישן וממזרת חדשה.
ger yashan u'mamzeres chadasha.
In the case of a גר ger after ten generations, he's an
old גר, ger, his גר ger identity is way in the past,
and this person in front of us is somebody with a newly
minted ממזר mamzer identity. So that creates a problem, somebody who we
treat as a ישראל Yisrael with somebody who we know as a
ממזר, mamzer, and that's why you can't have that allowed, a גר
אחר עשרה דורות. ger achar asara doros. אמרי, Amri, people will say,
בר ישראל הוא, bar Yisrael hu, he's a straight ישראל, Yisrael, דקנסיב
ממזרת. de'k'nasiv mamzeres. So that's the problem of גר אחר עשרה דורות.
ger achar asara doros. הכא, Hacha, in this case, אידי ואידי כהדדי
הנהו, idi v'idi ke'haddi hanu, they're all the same פרשה. parsha. If
you the reason you're call if the reason you're calling them ספק
ממזר safek mamzer is because you're applying the label of כותי. Kuti.
Once you apply the label of כותי, Kuti, the identity of גר
ger goes with the label of כותי. Kuti. If you say it
was so many generations ago and we're going to forget the גר
ger label, the כותי Kuti גר ger label, then you should forget
the כותי Kuti ממזר mamzer label. So how do you split your
vote? So we still don't understand why a כותי Kuti can't marry
a כותי. Kuti. So כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי אליעזר, ki
ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Eliezer, שמע לה אמר, shama lei amar,
he said, רבי אליעזר סבר לה כרבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Eliezer savar lah
k'Rabbi Yishmael, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds like רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
turn the page. ורבי ישמעאל סבר לה כרבי עקיבא, Ve'Rabbi Yishmael savar
lah k'Rabbi Akiva, and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael holds like רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Now what does this mean? רבי אליעזר סבר לה כרבי
ישמעאל דאמר, Rabbi Eliezer savar lah k'Rabbi Yishmael de'amar, כותים גרי אריות
הן. Kutim gerei arayos hein. Number one, holds like רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, רש"י Rashi says we have no idea where רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael said this, but whatever, the גמרא Gemara understood that רבי ישמעאל's
Rabbi Yishmael position was that כותים Kutim are converts due to the
lions, meaning that they're not sincere converts. They did it out of
fear and they're really non-Jews. Okay. ורבי Ve'Rabbi now if they're all
non-Jews, what do we care who they marry? Let them marry one
another, what's it our issue? Okay. Number two though, ורבי ישמעאל סבר
לה כרבי עקיבא דאמר, Ve'Rabbi Yishmael savar lah k'Rabbi Akiva de'amar, עובד
כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד ממזר. oved kochavim ve'eved ha'ba
al bas Yisrael havlad mamzer. No, the problem was was that Jewish
women intermarried with כותים. Kutim. So the children would be ממזרים mamzerim
if you hold like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right? That says a
slave or non-Jew with a Jewish woman, the child is a ממזר.
mamzer. Everybody with me? So the כותים Kutim are non-Jews, non-Jews who
think they're Jews. Jewish women married in. So what are the kids?
ממזרים. mamzerim. So that's why כותים Kutim can't marry זה בזה. zeh
b'zeh. Now the question is, you should be telling me what? We
basically have a population here that is non-Jews mixed in with them
is a certain percentage of Jewish ממזרים. mamzerim. Okay. Right, so the
reason כותים Kutim can't marry זה בזה zeh b'zeh is because what
we're really saying is any Jews among you who might be descendant
of Jewish mothers, you're still Jewish and therefore don't marry somebody there
because
they're
not Jews, not because you're a ממזר. mamzer. Why do we have
to mention they're ממזרים? mamzerim? It's just
Jews intermingled with non-Jews and therefore don't marry one another because you
might be a Jew marrying a non-Jew. So תוספות Tosafos rays... So
תוספות Tosfos raises this question,
okay? And it's not clear what תוספות Tosfos answers, but what I
need to say to you is that there's a cryptic part of
תוספות's Tosfos answer where it sounds like and the מהרש"א Maharsha develops
this or the מהרש"א Maharsha rejects this as a read of תוספות,
Tosfos, but it becomes a possibility which is: when the גמרא Gemara
says, what's the alternative of saying עבד הבא על בת ישראל, עבד
וגוי הבא על בת ישראל, הולד ממזר? Eved haba al bas Yisroel,
Eved vegoi haba al bas Yisroel, havlad mamzer? Do you
remember what the alternative is? What do we say about an עבד
Eved or a non-Jew that has sex with a Jewish woman? What
do we say the child is? Not ממזר, mamzer, how do we
פוסק, posken, does anybody remember this? Hello? What?
Well, the גמרא Gemara says כשר. Kasher. I mean
כשר, Kasher, whatever, okay? So the question is, people listen to this,
it's an important point, okay?
There's a read of one of the בעלי התוספות Baalei HaTosfos that
says that if a non-Jew or a slave has sex with a
Jewish woman, when the גמרא Gemara says the child is not a
ממזר mamzer but כשר, Kasher, it does not mean that the child
is Jewish. It means the child is a non-Jew and not a
ממזר. mamzer. So he's כשר Kasher in the sense that he has
the ability to convert and then he'll be okay, which is better
than a ממזר mamzer who's stuck as a ממזר mamzer status. Now
take a minute and take a step back and realize what that
just said. That just said that our idea of matrilineal descent, that
it doesn't matter who the father is, according to one very, very
tiny read of a ראשון Rishon in the גמרא Gemara is that
no, either the child is a ממזר mamzer if the father's a
non-Jew or the child's a non-Jew. When the גמרא Gemara says כשר,
Kasher, it doesn't mean Jew. It means
non-ממזר mamzer because it's a non-Jew. So there's actually one position of
one of the בעלי התוספות Baalei HaTosfos that says that there's no
such thing as matrilineal descent unless you got both parents as Jews,
the child's a non-Jew.
Unless you got both parents.
Not patrilineal, it's bilineal or whatever it is.
Now that read would say that's why the גמרא Gemara here had
to say the child was a ממזר mamzer because the alternative to
the child being a ממזר mamzer is not the child being a
Jew, but the child being a non-Jew. So if we said כותים
Kutim are non-Jews and if we say the child of them with
a Jewish woman is a non-ממזר, mamzer, according to this read we'd
be saying the child is a non-Jew. So then they're all non-Jews,
so what do we care? So the only way to say that
there was a problem with כותים Kutim was to say they were
non-Jews, the children that they had with Jewish women were Jews, and
therefore it's a Jew-non-Jew problem. And that's the position that the child
is a ממזר mamzer because the alternative to that is that the
child's a non-Jew. Okay, so I just raise that to be aware,
we certainly don't פוסק posken that way, which is like a good
thing. Oh my God, could you imagine, right, if we basically said
forget matrilineal descent like everybody, both parents have to be Jewish? Maybe
there's some people who want to say that, I don't know. Anyway,
but this is, anyway, but that is, but no, overwhelmingly of course
that's not how we read and certainly not how we פוסק, posken,
but I did want to tell you that that does come up
in this discussion because it's a bizarre גמרא. Gemara. Because according to
this read the problem of כותים Kutim marrying זה בזה zeh bazeh
is not that the kid is a ממזר. mamzer. The problem of
כותים Kutim marrying זה בזה zeh bazeh is that you have Jews
mixed in with non-Jews. Okay, anyway, that's one answer. Let's read a
little bit further in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ומי סבר לה רבי ישמעאל כרבי עקיבא? Umi savar lah
Rabbi Yishmael k'Rabbi Akiva? Does רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael really hold like
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, meaning that the idea that a child of
a Jewish mother and non-Jewish father is a ממזר? mamzer? ואמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי ישמעאל, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yishmael, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says in the name of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, מניין
לעובד כוכבים ועבד שבא על הכהנת ועל הלויה ועל בת ישראל שפסלה?
Minaayin l'Oved Kochavim ve'Eved sheba al haKohenes ve'al haLeviya ve'al bas Yisroel
shepasilah?
How do you know if a non-Jew or slave had sex with
a Jewish woman, כהנת, Kohenes, לויה, Leviya, בת ישראל, bas Yisroel, that
they invalidate her, make her אסור assur to a כהן, make her
like a חללה chalala or a זונה? zona? שנאמר ובת כהן כי
תהיה אלמנה וגרושה וזרע אין לה. Shene'emar uvas Kohen ki sihiyeh almanah
ugerusha vezera ein lah.
The daughter of a כהן, if she's a widow or divorcee and
she has no children, she goes back to her father's house and
continues to eat תרומה. terumah. Okay, so the דרשה drasha is: so
he has sex with a man but now she's divorced from him,
now she goes back to her father's house, so she remains in
her kosher status. When does she remain in her kosher status? מי
שיש לו אלמנות וגרושין. Mi sheyesh lo almanus ugerushin. Only if the
man that she left is a man that there she could become
a widow or divorcee from, meaning that there was a kosher קידושין.
kiddushin. It was a, or at least קידושין kiddushin was possible. יצא
עובד כוכבים ועבד. Yatza Oved Kochavim ve'Eved.
However, if she had sex with a non-Jew or slave where divorced
and widowhood is not possible because she could never in theory be
married to them, שאין לו אלמנות וגרושין, she'ein lo almanus ugerushin, in
that case she never goes back to her father's house because sex
with a man which she could not have קידושין kiddushin invalidates her,
makes her a חללה chalala or makes her a זונה. zona. Okay,
so that's. Okay, fine. So he says that the sex with this
man invalidated. How does it show that that's not רבי עקיבא? Rabbi
Akiva? Because what would רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say? If a Jewish
woman had sex with an עבד eved or a non-Jew, what would
the child be? ממזר. mamzer. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
say, if the child's a ממזר, mamzer, of course the mother is
פסול. pasul. You don't need to make a דרשה drasha from a
פסוק. pasuk. ואי סלקא דעתך סבר לה כרבי עקיבא, ve-ee salka datach
savar lah ke-Rabbi Akiva, if you think he holds like רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, השתא ממזר הוי, hashta mamzer havay, if the kid would
be a ממזר, mamzer, מיפסל בביאתו מיבעיא? mipsal b'viato mibaya? You don't
need a דרשה drasha to tell me the mother becomes פסול. pasul.
So clearly רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael who says that כותים Kutim are
non-Jews, does not hold that the kid is a ממזר. mamzer. אלא
Ela
fine. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael doesn't hold it. But רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, remember this is all רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that says כותים
Kutim can't marry כותים. Kutim. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar holds both positions.
רבי אלעזר סבר לה כרבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Elazar savar lah ke-Rabbi Ishmael,
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar first holds like רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, דאמר
כותים גירי אריות, d'amar Kutim gerei arayot, that כותים Kutim are non-Jews,
וסבר כרבי עקיבא ve-savar ke-Rabbi Akiva דאמר עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על
בת ישראל הולד ממזר, d'amar oved kochavim ve-eved ha-ba al bat Yisrael
ha-velad mamzer, and holds like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says the
kids that they would have with Jewish women would be ממזרים. mamzerim.
So we're back to the square one, except we're not saying it's
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael holds of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we're saying
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar holds of both positions. So according to רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, כותים Kutim are non-Jews mixed with Jewish ממזרים, mamzerim,
and therefore they can't marry זה בזה. zeh ba-zeh. Forget the ממזר,
mamzer, just because it's Jews and non-Jews. But it's Jews and non-Jews
mixed with Jewish ממזרים. mamzerim. Let's just read one more line. The
גמרא Gemara says, ומי סבר לה רבי אלעזר כרבי עקיבא? u-mi savar
lah Rabbi Elazar ke-Rabbi Akiva? One minute. How can you say רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar holds like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that the child
is a ממזר mamzer of a Jewish woman and a non-Jewish man?
והאמר רבי אלעזר, ve-ha-amar Rabbi Elazar, אף על פי שנחלקו בית שמאי
ובית הלל בצרות, af al pi she-necheleku Beit Shammai u-Beit Hillel be-tzarot,
remember the first משנה Mishna in יבמות Yevamot where the question is,
is the co-wife of a woman who's an ערוה erva does she
require יבום yibbum or חליצה? chalitzah? Right, anybody vaguely remember that? Big
debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit Hillel u-Beit Shammai, and then
became the whole question, could בית הלל Beit Hillel marry the daughters
of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and vice versa because maybe somebody did
a חליצה chalitzah that wasn't necessary or didn't do a חליצה chalitzah
that was, or did a יבום yibbum that wasn't allowed. Anyway, it
says even though there's all those debates and you might start to
wonder what the status is of the children,
nevertheless, מודי באלו שאין ממזר אלא ממי שאיסורו איסור ערוה וענוש כרת.
modi be-elu she-ein mamzer ela mi mi she-issuro issur ervah ve-anush karet.
A child does not become a ממזר mamzer unless it is an
ערוה erva איסור. issur. If it's just a לאו lav איסור, issur,
like for example if a woman required חליצה chalitzah and she went
and married another man, that's a איסור לאו. issur lav. לא תהיה
אשת המת החוצה. lo tihyeh eshet ha-met ha-chutzah. That's not an עריות.
arayot. It's not an איסור כרת issur karet for a woman who
required חליצה chalitzah to marry another man. So his point is, don't
go overboard, even though some people say, oh, in this case she
needed חליצה chalitzah and she didn't do חליצה chalitzah and she married
another man, the child isn't a ממזר. mamzer. The child's only going
to be a ממזר mamzer by an איסור כרת. issur karet.
That's why I asked her earlier. Right, since when we use the
term ממזר mamzer we're talking about the full...
Yeah, but the full scope is not an איסור לאו, issur lav,
it's an איסור כרת. issur karet. איסור כרת ואיסור מיתה, issur karet
ve-issur mitah, not the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva איסור לאו. issur lav.
And that's the point. How can you say that רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar says the problem with כותים Kutim are ממזרים mamzerim mixed with
כותים Kutim with non-Jews? He doesn't hold that the kid would be
a ממזר. mamzer. He doesn't agree to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
the kid of an איסור לאו issur lav is a ממזר. mamzer.
Only the kid of an איסור כרת issur karet is a ממזר.
mamzer. So he would not say that the child of a Jewish
woman with a non-Jewish man is a ממזר mamzer because that's not
an איסור כרת. issur karet. Okay? So he doesn't have the ממזר
mamzer problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so we still so
we don't know what the reason is why he holds that כותים
Kutim cannot marry כותים. Kutim. So we're going to end here with
that question. Why can כותים Kutim not marry כותים? Kutim? One reason
is they're all ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim. But the גמרא Gemara says,
but they're ספק ממזרים safek mamzerim and they're all גרים. gerim. So
that shouldn't be a problem. So answer number two is fine, they're
ממזרים mamzerim with non-Jews. Okay, which really just means they're Jews and
non-Jews. But anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says, but according to רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar they're not ממזרים. mamzerim. Okay? Even if it's a
Jewish woman and a non-Jewish man, the kid isn't a ממזר. mamzer.
So it's so what is your problem according to רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar that כותים Kutim cannot marry other כותים? Kutim? Okay, so we
will return tomorrow to find out the answer.
Leave you with a cliffhanger.